## Motivation letter

I hereby apply for the position 24/2017, Open Science Blog Editor.

I used to work in fundamental research (neuro-genetics, my second post doc - 2009 to 2014- was under Bjoern Brembs supervision), and got more interested in project management and pragmatic ways to improve scientific outputs in the recent years. I have been running the blog for Drososhare GmbH since 2014, and I am using twitter intensively in relation to my work there (@drososhare), and for my open science projects (@j\_colomb). I am for instance involved in the production of a MOOC for open science. I have a strong commitment to open data and other aspects of reproducible research standards (open access, reproducible reports, pre-registrationg). Please have a look at the links for more information.

Working for the OSL would be a great pleasure and opportunity, I could finally focus my attention and work on pushing open science forward (especially in Germany and in Europe), and get the means to have a real impact. I am in close contact with Dr Jon Tennant and we would like to discuss whether the position might be split, maybe between the two of us since our skills are complementary.

I am looking forward to hear from you, Dr. Julien Colomb

Links:

My website on teaching open science:

https://reproducibleresearch.wordpress.com/

The video pitch for my open science workshop:

https://vimeo.com/216695191

The open science meetup I am co-organising:

http://www.meetup.com/Berlin-Open-Science-Meetup/

The Drososhare blog:

https://drososhare.wordpress.com/

Referees:

Prof. Bjoern Brembs, bjoern@brembs.net

## Curriculum Vitae

Julien COLOMB, PhD in Biology Schillerpromenade 4 12049 Berlin julien.colomb@fu-berlin.de

https://github.com/jcolomb http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3127-5520

Birth: 9 April 1979 in Sion (CH) Married, two children Swiss



## Summary

After 12 years spent in fundamental research (neuro-genetics), during which I gathered skills in experimental design, team leading and student teaching, I got most interested in open science and research reproducibility, as well as the digital tools helping scientists to achieve it. I gathered extra experience in business development through the foundation of Drososhare, which turn out not to be sustainable yet. Since the birth of my second child, I am trying to make a living out of freelance work as data analyst and teaching reproducible research.

#### $Commercial\ activities$

2016-present Freelance scientist (data analysis and project management),

2012-present Founder and CEO of Drososhare GmbH (Berlin, Germany),

### Non-commercial activities

2015- present Organisation of the Berlin Open Science meetup:

Discussion on open science themes (Reproducible Research, Open Access, peer

review), and Organisation of the open con satellite conferences

2017- present Part of the march for science Berlin Orga team:

Organisation of a protest in Berlin in 2017 (11000 people came) and further

discussion on future actions

#### Research activities

2015 - 2016	Postdoctoral fellow, HU & Charité (Berlin, Germany), by Prof. Y. Winter
2014 - 2015	Postdoctoral fellow, HU & Charite (Berlin, Germany), by Prof. Y. Winter
2009 -2013	Postdoctoral fellow, FU (Berlin, Germany), by Prof. B. Brembs
2007-2008	Postdoctoral fellow ESPCI (Paris France) by Dr T Preat

#### Education

2016	FELASA B. HU Berlin
2013	Moderation & management (Continuing Education), FU Berlin/Artop.
2006	PhD in Biology, University of Fribourg ( <b>Fribourg</b> , Switzerland).
	PhD dissertation: "The chemosensory system of Drosophila larvae: neu-
	roanatomy and behaviour" Thesis director: Prof. R.F Stocker
2002	Diploma in Biology, University of Fribourg (Fribourg, Switzerland)
1998	"Maturité fédérale type C" (scientific subsection), in the "Collège de la royale
	Abbaye de St. Maurice"

## Languages

French (mother tongue), English (fluent), German (fluent), Spanish (basics).

## Research output

https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3127-5520 8 research papers (7 first author), 3 reviews, 1 Scienceopen collection https://github.com/jcolomb 3 Open source software (2 main author) h-index =7, Meeting Presentations = 25

## Supervision of student

2010-2014	Co-supervisor of the PhD student Christine Damrau (with Dr. B.Brembs) on
2008	the role of octopamine in reward, motivation and motor control in <i>Drosophila</i> . Co-supervisor of the PhD student Séverine Trannoy (with Dr. G. Isabel and
	Dr. N. Gervasi) on the role of dopamine in appetitive learning consolidation in
	Drosophila.
2005	Co-supervisor of the diploma work of Claire Huguenin (with Dr. A. Ramaekers)
	on the role of NO in olfactory discrimination in <i>Drosophila</i> larvae.

# Teaching experience

2016	Animal models of neuropathy, (master student, 2x2h lecture, organisation)
2012	Genetik (bachelor student, 2 x 3 h. lecture, 2x 1h. seminar)
2012	Neurogenetik. (master student, 2 x 2 h. lecture, 2x 1h. seminar)
2011	Practical course neurobiology. (7 x 4 h., Practical course supervision)
2011	Entwicklung der Insekten [Insect development] (2 h. lecture)
2006	Fluorescence and Confocal Microscopy (master student, 3h. lecture)
2003-2006	Studying behavior. (master student, 2 h. lecture)
2003-2005	Developmental- and Neurogenetics (master student, 2 h. lecture).

# Computer skills

Organisation and publication: OSX, Windows, Outlook, Access; , LATEX, Office; html; Image processing and scientific platform: Photoshop, Illustrator, Image J, Inscape; labfolder, figshare, github, overleaf, authorea, scienceopen Programming: R (advanced), Git, Labview

#### Other tasks

Creation of the T. Preat's and R.F. Stocker's lab website. Co-director in the theater group "les apostrophes" in 2006